okay lecture two processes
uh here you have the instructions for
what you need to read from the book
um and you also have the extra
faculty reading from the other book the
silvershots operating system concepts
if you want of course it's not mandatory
so the objective for this lecture is to
introduce the notion
of a process okay so a programming
execution
will describe the various features of
processes
we will start discussing a bit
scheduling too
and we will also explore inter-process
communication
so let's start with an introduction
about processes
i will start this lecture by
showing you two sentences and
telling you why both sentences are not
really correct okay
this is something we will uh discuss
during this lecture and the next one so
hopefully by the end of the
lecture about threads the next one
it should be clear why are these two
sentences
are not really correct so it's not
really true
that we run several programs at the same
time
we do but most of the times what is
happening
is that there is only one program
being run but which program is run
changes continuously and the change is
so fast
that you don't really perceive
the change yourself so you have the
feeling that program a and b are running
at the same time but actually it's
a then it's b then it's a and it's b the
change is so fast that for you it looks
like they are happening both at the same
time
in that sense it would be more correct
to say that there is
only one program that is being run by
each
cpu this is also not really true because
as we will discuss more in the next
lecture
what can actually run only one program
at the time
it's actually a cpu core okay and modern
cpus have multiple cores
so they could actually run several
things at the same time
okay uh so
if we want to be a bit more precise we
should say that we feel
many times that several programs run at
the same time
but it is indeed true that each cpu core
okay so sorry that one cpu can run
several
programs at the same time but only one
program at the time can be run by
each cpu core